A Finding Aid to the Ed Colker Papers, 1944-2020, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ed Colker papers
1944-2020
Archives of American Art
Colker, Ed, 1927-
AAA.colked
Archival Resource Key
3.4 Linear feet
The papers of painter, printmaker, educator and administrator Ed Colker are dated 1944-2020 and measure 3.4 linear feet. Colker's painting, printmaking, and Haybarn Press, as well as his career as an art teacher and university administrator, are documented through biographical materials, correspondence, interviews, writings, subject files, printed material, and photographs. There is a 0.2 linear ft. addition to the collection donated in 2020 that includes lists of works of art, exhibition information, letters to Colker, talks and lecutres by Colker, printed material and miscellany.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter, printmaker, educator and administrator Ed Colker are dated 1944-2020 and measure 3.4 linear feet. Colker's painting, printmaking, and Haybarn Press, as well as his career as an art teacher and university administrator, are documented through biographical materials, correspondence, interviews, writings, subject files, printed material, and photographs. There is a 0.2 linear ft. addition to the collection donated in 2020 that includes lists of works of art, exhibition information, letters to Colker, talks and lecutres by Colker, printed material and miscellany.
Biographical materials include official letters regarding Colker's performance in the Army, caricatures of him, diplomas, resume, awards, and certificates.
Correspondence, mainly professional in nature with a few scattered personal letters, concerns Colker's academic and artistic work, Haybarn Editions, exhibitions, projects, and various interests. Poet correspondents are J. Curtis Johnson, Kathleen Norris, Deborah Pease, and Jeanne Walker; translators include Melvin Konner and others.
Interviews with Ed Colker, conducted between 1982 and 2008 for various purposes, are preserved as 1 sound cassette and published transcripts. Also found are 1 sound cassette, 1 videocassette, and a published transcript of interviews Colker conducted with Will Barnet and Toshiko Takaezu in 1981 and 1994 respectively.
Among Colker's writings are the published versions of several articles and the manuscript of an unpublished one; two proposed books for students of design and typography; lectures delivered to students (3 videocassettes), miscellaneous writings, notes, and 1 videocassete of readings by artists from one of Colker's Haybarn Press poetry portfolios.
Subject files document many of Colker's professional interests, activities, projects, and relationships. Also of note are files about Haybarn Press.
The bulk of the printed material consists of exhibition catalogs, announcements, and school catalogs. Almost all is about or mentions Colker, or features reproductions of his work. Of note is the first and only issue of Re-Art: A Reflection of Current Ideas on the Arts (1954), published by Colker and Gene Feldman.
Photographs are of Colker and his family; Colker at events related to his artistic, academic, and publishing activities; artwork by Colker, and his work as reproduced in Haybarn Editions. Also found are an exterior view of the barn studio and one of printers working at Desjobert Press.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ed Colker in 1991, 2013 and 2020.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original material requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical / Historical
Ed Colker (b. 1927) is a painter, printmaker, educator, and administrator who has worked in Chicago, Philadelphia, and New York City. Colker founded the not-for-profit fine art publisher Haybarn Press. He is married to artist Elaine Galen and resides in Mt. Kisco, NY.
After high school, Colker was awarded a scholarship and began his art education at the Pennsylvania Museum School of Industrial Arts. He interrupted his studies to serve in the U.S. Army (1944-1946). He graduated in 1949, by which time the school had become the Philadelphia Museum School of Art; today it is the University of the Arts. He taught art in the Philadelphia area before moving to New York City in 1956. Later, Colker earned degrees from New York University (B.S. Ed, 1964; M.A., 1985).
Colker taught art and design courses at the University of Pennsylvania, University of Illinois at Chicago Circle, Cornell University, Pratt Institute, and Philadelphia College of Art. By the 1980s, he had become an administrator as well as a professor. Throughout his academic career, Colker published and lectured widely, served as a visiting artist, acted as a consultant, and participated in professional organizations. He occasionally organized exhibitions and served on exhibition juries.
Since 1960, under the imprints Editions du Grenier, Haybarn Editions, and Haybarn Press, Colker has published limited edition books, portfolios, broadsides, individual pages, and folders of poetry. Most are accompanied by Colker's etchings and lithographs inspired by the texts. Haybarn Press, under the Ambor Edition imprint, also produced four portfolios with text and drawings by Elaine Galen, 1996-2008. From its inception, the work of Haybarn Press has been featured in many exhibitions of book arts. Colker also participated in group shows throughout the United States and enjoyed solo exhibitions of his paintings and prints. Haybarn Press productions and Colker's prints and paintings are in the permanent collections of Brown University, Cornell University, Harvard University, Library of Congress, Museum of Modern Art, New York Public Library, University of Arizona Museum of Art, and others.
Now retired from university administration and teaching, Colker continues to operate Haybarn Press and occasionally serves as an exhibition juror and visiting artist.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1946-circa 2011 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence,1954-2011 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Interviews, 1981-2008 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1961-1990s (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Subject files, 1952-2013 (Boxes 2-3; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material,1944-2011 (Box 3; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1960s-2010 (Box 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Unprocessed Addition, circa 1963-2020 (Box 5; 0.2 linear feet)
Printmakers -- United States; Interviews; Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- United States; Printing; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Art -- Study and teaching; Transcripts; Design; Arts administrators -- United States; Painters -- United States; Educators -- United States; Takaezu, Toshiko; Pease, Deborah; Atelier Desjobert; Walker, Jeanne Murray; United States. Army; Haybarn Press; Konner, Melvin; Barnet, Will, 1911-2012; Norris, Kathleen, 1947-; Johnson, J. Curtis
- Biographical Materials, 1946-circa 2011; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes two letters of commendation from the 349th Infantry Headquarters, diplomas, a resume, and two printed caricatures of Colker by students. Also found are various awards and certificates including The Academy of American Poets membership certificate identifying Colker as a founding member. Several items are photocopies.
  - Biographical Materials, 1946-circa 2011; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1954-2011; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is arranged by year.
  Correspondence, mainly professional in nature with a few scattered personal letters, concerns Colker's academic and artistic work, Haybarn Editions, exhibitions, projects, and various interests. It includes arrangements for lectures, artist in residence appointments, jurying exhibitions, and consulting. Among the correspondents are universities, libraries, galleries, museums; poetry, printmaking, and book arts organizations, as well as groups relevant to his work as an artist, educator, and university administrator. Poet correspondents are J. Curtis Johnson, Kathleen Norris, Deborah Pease, and Jeanne Walker; translators include Melvin Konner and others.
  - Correspondence, undated; 1954-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-9)
  - Poets, 2003-2011; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Translators, 2006-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Interviews, 1981-2008; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  The 1982 interview with Ed Colker was published in The Load, SUNY College at Purchase's student newspaper as part of a feature story about a three-day campus event,"A Celebration of the Book as Art." The interview Irving Sandler conducted with Ed Colker (1 sound cassette) took place in New York City during the summer of 1985 while Colker's exhibition was on view at Neuberger Museum, Purchase, NY; in 1999, its transcript was published in conjunction with the exhibition Ed Colker: Prints for Poetry and Prose (1990 June 26 – August 3) at the University Art Gallery, State University of New York at Albany. Robert McCamant's interview of Colker was published as "Caxtonians Collect: Ed Colker" in the May 2008 issue of Caxtonian, the club's newsletter.
  An interview Colker conducted with Will Barnet (1 sound cassette) was published as "Reflections on Fifty Years of Teaching: An Interview with Will Barnet," part of an article titled "Independent Art Schools: Traditions and Departures," Art Journal (Spring 1982). The Toshiko Takaezu interview (1 videocassette), which Colker conducted for Cooper Union students, took place at her studio/home in New Jersey.
  - Interviews with Colker, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Interview with Ed Colker and Margot Lovejoy conducted by David Schwartz (transcript), 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Interview with Ed Colker conducted by Irving Sandler, 1985; Archival Resource Key; 1 sound cassette; transcript (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Interview with Ed Colker conducted by Robert McCamant (transcript), 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Interviews conducted by Colker, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Interview with Will Barnet conducted by Ed Colker, 1981; Archival Resource Key; 1 sound cassette; transcript (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Interview with Toshiko Takaezu conducted by Ed Colker, circa 1994; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Writings, 1961-1990s; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings by Colker include: printed versions of articles and the manuscript of an unpublished article about printmaking in the U.S.; two proposed books for students of design and typography; 3 videocassettes of lectures delivered to students at the University of Illinois, Chicago Circle, Pratt Institute, and University of the Arts, and other venues; miscellaneous writing; panel discussion notes; a videocassete of artists reading from one of Colker's poetry portfolios.
  - Articles, 2007-2008; 1961-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Book about Typography for Students of Design and Typography, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key; Dismantled binder (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Book, "Design and Expression: An Introduction to Elements of Visual Communication" (dismantled binder), circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key; Dismantled binder (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Lectures, Texts, 1972-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lectures, Recordings, 1990s; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; 1977-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Panel Discussion, Marist College, "The Art of Collaboration" Remarks, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Readings by Artists from Colker's Portfolio Four Poets/Poems presented at Cooper Union, circa 1993; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Subject Files, 1952-2013; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Subject files maintained by Colker document many of his professional interests, activities, projects, and relationships. Files are comprised of correspondence, printed material, writings, photographs and miscellaneous items in varying combinations. Of particular interest is the file concerning the Art Journal Editing Project. Colker was guest editor of an issue on "Education of the Artist." The file includes responses from Pat Adams, Lawrence Alloway, Eleanor Antinova, Grace Hartigan, Vera Klement, Philip Pearlstein, Peter Plagens and Martin Puryear, to the question: "What are you saying or introducing as major currents to students today that have changed from a few years ago and what events or dynamics have generated your reconsiderations? (If you are holding and reinforcing constants, please indicate that, too.)" Other subjects of interest include Haybarn Press; poets Michael A. Anina, Catherine Kasper, and Kathleen Norris; and Dave Brubeck, whose music inspired a Haybarn Edition. This series contains one audiovisual recording titled "National Endowment for the Arts/Getty Art Program Tape," the pilot for a proposed PBS television program on the arts for children and their parents for which Colker served as a consultant.
  Subject files are alphabetized by title. Additional material relating to many of the individuals and organizations documented by subject files may be found with correspondence (Series 2) and among the printed material (Series 6).
  - Anina, Michael A., circa 1977-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Art Journal Editing Project, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Bates College Museum of Art, 1995-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Benningham, Peter, 1999-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Brubeck, Dave and Iola, 1963-2011; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Center for Book Arts, 1977-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chicago Center for Book and Paper Arts, Five Decades in Print: Ed Colker (1999 July 2-30), Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dane, William J., 2007-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Douglas Kenyon Gallery, Chicago, Ed Colker Paintings and Prints (1975 March 14-April 18), Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Feldman, Eugene, circa 1975-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Geigy Pharmaceuticals Exhibitions, Ed Colker Co-curator, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Haybarn Press – Bulletins to Subscribers and Collectors, 1989-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Haybarn Press – Elephants by Night, 2005-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Haybarn Press – Publication Announcements, 1973-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hejduk, John, 1995-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hunterdon Art Center, 1969-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Illinois Arts Council, First Illinois Print Commission Program (copies 1973-1984), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - International Graphic Arts Society, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Kasper, Catherine, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Kaye College Course, The Creative Process: Exploration of the Landscape, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Kray, Elizabeth, 1970-1987; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Longwood Center for the Visual Arts Collaborative Workshop for Writers and Artists, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Murphy, Bill, undated; 2001-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - National Endowment for the Arts/Getty Art Program Tape 1, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Neuberger Museum, 1985-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Neuberger Museum, Five Decades in Print: Ed Colker (1999 February 6-April 9), 1998-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Norris, Kathleen, 1992-2008; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - The North Carolina Center for the Advancement of Teaching, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1952-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Poets House, 2000-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Print Club of New York, Inc., 2004-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Print Club (Philadelphia), 1952-2011; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Richard Florsheim Art Fund, 1996-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - State University of New York College at Purchase, 1980-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sultzkever, Abraham, 2003-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - University of Illinois at Chicago Circle, 1972-1989; 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Vanderbilt University Campus Visit, 2005-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - von Mochzisker, Bertha, 2001-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Worcester Art Museum, 1992-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Zigrosser, Carl, circa 1965-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Printed Material, 1944-2011; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 3
  Almost all printed material is about or mentions Colker, or includes reproductions of his work. Miscellaneous items include press releases, announcements of benefit auctions, notice of an international competition for which Colker was a juror. School catalogs are from years and institutions where Colker was a student, teacher, or administrator. Publications produced by Colker are a photocopy of the first and only issue of Re-Art: A Reflection of Current Ideas on the Arts (1954), published by Colker and Gene Feldman, and Architectural Photographs by Richard Nickel.
  - Articles, circa 1943-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Book, The Candles of Your Eyes by James Purdy, illustrated by Ed Colker, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Announcements, Reviews, etc., circa 1950s-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15-21)
  - Exhibition Catalogs – Colker, Co-curator, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1976-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Notices/Programs for Lectures, Talks, Events, circa 1969-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Publications produced by Colker, circa 1954; 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Reproductions, Artwork by Colker and Others, 1986-1991; 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Reproductions, New Years Cards sent by Ed Colker and Elaine Galen, 2000-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - School Catalogs, 1944-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28-30)
- Photographs, circa 1960s-2010; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 4
  Views of Colker and family prior to the 1960s are either color photocopies or prints of scanned images. There is a photograph of Colker in a life drawing class at the Philadelphia Museum School of Industrial Art and several views of him in Italy with the 349th Infantry, 88th Division during and soon after World War II, and in his studio. He appears alone and with students, colleagues, friends, and wife Elaine Galen. Many photographs record Colker at events related to his artistic, academic, and publishing activities. Other photographs are of artwork by Colker and his work as reproduced in Haybarn Editions. Exterior views of the barn studio and Desjobert Press are digitial prints.
  - People, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - Family (1920s), circa 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Ed Colker (1944-2010), circa 1960s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Ed Colker at Events, 1982-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Artwork by Colker, Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - Drawing (executed 1945), circa 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Paintings and Wood Constructions, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Paintings, 1970s-circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Prints, circa 1960s-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Reproductions in Haybarn Editions, circa 1960s-circa 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Barn Studio and House, Hampton, NJ (1966-1970); Desjobert Press (1966), Alain, M. Borr, Roger printing Ed's Lithos, circa 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Unprocessed Addition, circa 1963-2020; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet
  - Unprocessed Papers, Archival Resource Key (Box 5)